<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>CCA Blog - Daniel Gibson</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/feeds/daniel-gibson.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://columbusclassical.org/blog/</id><updated>2022-12-20T10:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>On the Importance of Struggle in a Good Education</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-the-importance-of-struggle-in-a-good-education.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-20T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-20T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-12-20:/blog/on-the-importance-of-struggle-in-a-good-education.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shouldn&amp;rsquo;t school be fun? Don&amp;rsquo;t children do better when they are having a good time? Why must an excellent education be difficult? Despite appearances, these are questions of ends, not means&amp;mdash;of purpose, not pedagogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Struggle is an inherent part of classical education, not gratuitously but teleologically. Students …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shouldn&amp;rsquo;t school be fun? Don&amp;rsquo;t children do better when they are having a good time? Why must an excellent education be difficult? Despite appearances, these are questions of ends, not means&amp;mdash;of purpose, not pedagogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Struggle is an inherent part of classical education, not gratuitously but teleologically. Students must acquire knowledge that they do not naturally possess and form character that they will not naturally develop. This requires hard work and discipline on the part of teacher and student alike. But the result is a lasting capacity for genuine happiness&amp;mdash;what Aristotle called &amp;ldquo;that activity of the soul in accord with virtue.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has learned to play a musical instrument well understands this. A good pianist diligently practices scales and arpeggios, not because it is fun or easy, but because doing so yields technical mastery and provides the foundations for appreciation of music theory. The toil serves a worthy end. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sisyphus is miserable on account of the futility of his task, not its difficulty. He lacks hope, not because the stone is heavy but because he carries it nowhere. Camus insisted that we must imagine Sisyphus happy, but of course, he is not. Modern education invites him to simply put down the rock and play in the sand&amp;mdash;but the futility remains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical schools recognize that it is only sincere struggle with a noble purpose that makes for true happiness. To paraphrase Lewis: &amp;ldquo;Aim for virtue and you will get fun &amp;lsquo;thrown in&amp;rsquo;; aim for fun and you will get neither.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>On Holding Sudents’ Emotions Accountable to the Truth</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-holding-sudents-emotions-accountable-to-the-truth.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-15T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-15T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-12-15:/blog/on-holding-sudents-emotions-accountable-to-the-truth.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever wonder why disagreement now seems impossible? Why debate only leads to greater conflict, not greater clarity? It is the inevitable consequence of generations of Americans being taught to seek and to love themselves rather than the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical education restores reason to its rightful place in the ordering of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever wonder why disagreement now seems impossible? Why debate only leads to greater conflict, not greater clarity? It is the inevitable consequence of generations of Americans being taught to seek and to love themselves rather than the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical education restores reason to its rightful place in the ordering of man&amp;rsquo;s faculties, not by teaching that feelings shouldn&amp;rsquo;t matter, but by recognizing that neither should they rule. As C.S. Lewis recognized: &amp;ldquo;The heart never takes the place of the head; but it can, and should, obey it.&amp;rdquo; We teach students the broad body of human knowledge&amp;mdash;literature, history, philosophy, natural science, mathematics, Latin, the arts&amp;mdash;to develop in them both the capacity and the desire to hold their emotions accountable to the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern education endeavors to make students feel good, not to help make them become good. So opinions are expressed by declaring &amp;ldquo;I feel&amp;rdquo; rather than &amp;ldquo;I think,&amp;rdquo; and experiences described as &amp;ldquo;my truths,&amp;rdquo; impervious to contradiction, all in the name of emotional health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet divorced from the truth, disagreements are little more than a battle of feelings versus feelings, resolvable only by power, not persuasion&amp;mdash;by force, not philosophy. Teaching the young to shout their feelings more loudly rather than to think about them more clearly cannot restore the deliberation, reflection, and choice that is the foundation of a free and flourishing republic. We must begin teaching our children to know and to love the truth again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disagree with me? Wonderful. Think I am wrong? Even better. But let&amp;rsquo;s stop pretending that we just feel differently.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Humble Pursuit of True Beauty</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-the-humble-pursuit-of-true-beauty.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-08T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-08T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-12-08:/blog/on-the-humble-pursuit-of-true-beauty.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Believe that &amp;ldquo;beauty is in the eye of the beholder&amp;rdquo;? That Notre Dame Cathedral is considered more beautiful than a strip mall only on account of prevailing social norms? That when it comes to matters of aesthetics, &amp;ldquo;to each his own&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical schools part ways with modern education in their …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Believe that &amp;ldquo;beauty is in the eye of the beholder&amp;rdquo;? That Notre Dame Cathedral is considered more beautiful than a strip mall only on account of prevailing social norms? That when it comes to matters of aesthetics, &amp;ldquo;to each his own&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical schools part ways with modern education in their recognition that beauty is more than an arbitrary, personal sentiment or an imposed, social construct. We hold that beauty is objective and that one&amp;rsquo;s taste for the beautiful can either be well-ordered or disordered. The purpose of education in the arts is to form in students a knowledge and love of what is most beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, man&amp;rsquo;s understanding of beauty will always be imperfect and incomplete. But a lack of comprehensive knowledge of the beautiful does not render it incoherent. That science has never formulated an adequate &amp;ldquo;theory of everything&amp;rdquo; does not mean we know nothing of physics at all. It simply requires humility in the pursuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But consider the idea of music itself. The very distinction between a cacophony of sounds on the one hand, and musical expression on the other, is itself a rejection of modern conceptions of beauty. And no wonder. The word cacophony derives from the Greek kakophonos, meaning ill-sounding; the word music from the Greek mousike tekhne, meaning art of the muses. Are we really prepared to declare music class the mere study of noise?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is much beauty in the world. Let us be about the business of giving our children the eyes to see it and the ears to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>On What Makes a School Excellent</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-what-makes-a-school-excellent.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-01T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-01T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-12-01:/blog/on-what-makes-a-school-excellent.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What makes a school excellent? It starts with a recognition that equality &amp;ldquo;has no place in the world of the mind&amp;rdquo;. Yes, all men are created equal. But their ideas, philosophies, art, literature, governments, cultures are not. Sound pretentious, even anti-democratic? Consider the alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratizing knowledge yields not excellence, but …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What makes a school excellent? It starts with a recognition that equality &amp;ldquo;has no place in the world of the mind&amp;rdquo;. Yes, all men are created equal. But their ideas, philosophies, art, literature, governments, cultures are not. Sound pretentious, even anti-democratic? Consider the alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratizing knowledge yields not excellence, but a triumph of the mediocre and a taste for the ordinary. Such schooling can be &amp;ldquo;excellent&amp;rdquo; only in the same way that a bulldozer can be &amp;ldquo;excellent,&amp;rdquo; i.e., to the extent it is effective at abolishing distinctions and demolishing hierarchies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical schools teach every student not what is most appealing to democratic sensibilities, but what is most excellent for an educated citizen: Goethe, not Grisham; Prokofiev, not Presley; Machiavelli, not Maddow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As C.S. Lewis observed, &amp;ldquo;[b]eauty is not democratic; she reveals herself more to the few than to the many, more to the persistent and disciplined seekers than to the careless. Virtue is not democratic; she is achieved by those who pursue her more hotly than most men. Truth is not democratic; she demands special talents and special industry in those to whom she gives her favours. Political democracy is doomed if it tries to extend its demand for equality into these higher spheres. Ethical, intellectual, or aesthetic democracy is death. A truly democratic education&amp;mdash;one which will preserve democracy&amp;mdash;must be, in its own field, ruthlessly aristocratic, shamelessly &amp;lsquo;high-brow&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you desire an excellent education for your child? One befitting a citizen of our democratic republic? It begins with renewing our belief in excellence itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>Welcome!</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/welcome.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-16T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-16T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-08-16:/blog/welcome.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is my privilege to welcome you to Columbus Classical Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are honored and humbled by your interest in our school and grateful that you have considered entrusting us with the education of your children. It is a solemn and wonderful charge to impart to students the knowledge and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is my privilege to welcome you to Columbus Classical Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are honored and humbled by your interest in our school and grateful that you have considered entrusting us with the education of your children. It is a solemn and wonderful charge to impart to students the knowledge and virtue upon which responsible and joyful lives are built. Whether or not you ever enroll your child at CCA, we welcome you to explore our school and to inquire with us at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbus Classical Academy is a Hillsdale College Curriculum School, utilizing Hillsdale&amp;rsquo;s world-class and distinctively American, classical curriculum. Because we recognize that all education is both immanently personal and at the same time inherently social and political, students receive an education befitting not only a human being, but also an American citizen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hillsdale curriculum is rigorous, integrated, and sequential, grounded in the liberal arts and sciences and the Western canon. Every child studies literature, mathematics, history, civics, the natural sciences, Latin, the fine arts, physical education, and philosophy. These disciplines are taught using time-tested, teacher-led pedagogical methods, which include rigorous phonics instruction, explicit grammar lessons, and memorization and recitation. Instruction is complemented by the use of manipulatives in the teaching of arithmetic at the earliest grades. Handwriting and cursive lessons in written expression, use of the Socratic method, and close and critical reading of the classics and primary source texts are employed as students mature. At the conclusion of their time at CCA, students will possess a broad and deep body of knowledge about their world, their culture, their nation, and themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But CCA is more than just an academic institution. It is also a place of moral formation, where virtue is modeled, practiced, honored, and expected. We maintain that there are objective, moral laws to which all are accountable, and that without knowledge of the good and a desire to pursue it, man can be neither virtuous nor truly free. Our embrace of the classical virtues points us beyond ourselves to what is eternally significant, recognizing as did our nation&amp;rsquo;s founders that: &amp;ldquo;Religion, morality, and knowledge, being necessary to good government and the happiness of mankind, schools and the means of education shall forever be encouraged.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That proper, formal schooling is good and necessary, however, does not alone make it sufficient to the life of man. Parents are the first and primary teachers of their children. And because we at CCA hold that natural bond and relationship in high esteem, you will know what your children are learning, and your input on how best to engage and inspire them will be encouraged. Even more, your commitment to supporting and nurturing their moral and academic development at home will be essential. We are only a part of the task that is raising mature, joyful, responsible adults. We cannot do our part without you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an institution, Columbus Classical Academy is not yet a year old. But as an idea, as a philosophy of education, as &amp;ldquo;the real community of man, . . . of the potential knowers,&amp;rdquo; as Allan Bloom describes it, our school is more than 2,300 years old. We invite you to join us in the Great Conversation, to partner with us in passing down our incomparable cultural, religious and political inheritance to the next generation, and to pursue lives of knowledge and virtue together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to Columbus Classical Academy. &lt;em&gt;Veritas et Virtus.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;Daniel C. Gibson&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="News"></category></entry></feed>