<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Veritas et Virtus - Daniel C. Gibson</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/feeds/daniel-c-gibson.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://columbusclassical.org/blog/</id><updated>2023-04-25T10:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>On the Foundations of Self-Government</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-the-foundations-of-self-government.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-25T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-25T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Daniel C. Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2023-04-25:/blog/on-the-foundations-of-self-government.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="federalist" src="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/images/2023-04-25-federalist.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;View children as &amp;ldquo;little angels?&amp;rdquo; Believe they are naturally good, needing only to be encouraged to grow? This is the false foundation of progressive education&amp;mdash;and it has profound implications for self-government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinkers like Rousseau, Froebel, and Dewey changed the course of education in the West, introducing terms like &amp;ldquo;kindergarten …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="federalist" src="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/images/2023-04-25-federalist.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;View children as &amp;ldquo;little angels?&amp;rdquo; Believe they are naturally good, needing only to be encouraged to grow? This is the false foundation of progressive education&amp;mdash;and it has profound implications for self-government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinkers like Rousseau, Froebel, and Dewey changed the course of education in the West, introducing terms like &amp;ldquo;kindergarten&amp;rdquo; (a &amp;ldquo;garden of children&amp;rdquo;) and planting the seeds for the now-ubiquitous &amp;ldquo;growth mindset.&amp;rdquo; No wonder our never-ending &amp;ldquo;crisis&amp;rdquo; of democracy comes with a complete breakdown of behavioral norms in our schools. As C.S. Lewis recognized, we&amp;rsquo;ve placed the justification for self-government entirely on the wrong foundation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a democrat because I believe in the Fall of Man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think most people are democrats for the opposite reason. A great deal of democratic enthusiasm descends from the ideas of people like Rousseau, who believed in democracy because they thought mankind so wise and good that every one deserved a share in the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The danger of defending democracy on those grounds is that they&amp;rsquo;re not true. . .I find that they&amp;rsquo;re not true without looking further than myself. I don&amp;rsquo;t deserve a share in governing a hen-roost. Much less a nation. . .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real reason for democracy is just the reverse. Mankind is so fallen that no man can be trusted with unchecked power over his fellows. Aristotle said that some people were only fit to be slaves. I do not contradict him. But I reject slavery because I see no men fit to be masters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children are not angels. The American Founders understood this, observing in Federalist 51 that &amp;ldquo;[i]f men were angels, no government would be necessary.&amp;rdquo; That includes self-government. Unless we first acknowledge the depravity of man, we cannot even begin the process of educating him to be free.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Peculiar Importance of Teaching “Useless” Knowledge</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-the-peculiar-importance-of-teaching-useless-knowledge.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-18T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Daniel C. Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2023-04-18:/blog/on-the-peculiar-importance-of-teaching-useless-knowledge.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Think that a classical education imparts a great deal of knowledge that is neither useful nor practical? Believe that it often consists of subjects that are neither relevant to present concerns nor designed to accomplish tangible results? This view is not entirely mistaken&amp;mdash;but as Roger Scruton observed, a lofty …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Think that a classical education imparts a great deal of knowledge that is neither useful nor practical? Believe that it often consists of subjects that are neither relevant to present concerns nor designed to accomplish tangible results? This view is not entirely mistaken&amp;mdash;but as Roger Scruton observed, a lofty &amp;ldquo;irrelevance&amp;rdquo; is the indispensable feature of an excellent education, not a bug:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally a large part of learning was devoted to subjects that are wilfully 'irrelevant'&amp;mdash;such as Latin, Greek, ancient history, higher mathematics, philosophy and literary criticism. The syllabus recommended by ancient thinkers consisted almost entirely of such subjects. And the ancient instinct was wise. The more irrelevant the subject, the more lasting is the benefit that it confers. Irrelevant subjects bring understanding of the human condition, by forcing the student to stand back from it. They also enhance the appetite for life, by providing material for thought and conversation. This is the secret which civilization has guarded: that power and influence come through the acquisition of useless knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alternative&amp;mdash;i.e., an education that seeks incessantly to be contemporary and up-to-date, functional and relevant&amp;mdash;&amp;ldquo;keeps the student&amp;rsquo;s mind so narrowly focused on his random and transient&amp;hellip;convictions that, when he ceases to be obsessed with them, he will lack the education through which to discover what to put in their place.&amp;rdquo; In the end, as Allan Bloom saw firsthand, &amp;ldquo;[t]hey may become competent specialists, but they are flat-souled. The world is for them what it presents itself to the senses to be; it is unadorned by imagination and devoid of ideals.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But do not mistake an education in &amp;ldquo;useless&amp;rdquo; knowledge for a useless education. &amp;ldquo;A person with a classical or literary education...inhabits a transformed world and sees meaning where others see facts. He is equipped not just to change the world but to interpret it&amp;rdquo; (Roger Scruton, "The Virtue of Irrelevance", &lt;em&gt;The Times&lt;/em&gt;, 1983).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Liberating Constraints of Truth and Virtue</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-the-liberating-constraints-of-truth-and-virtue.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-11T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-11T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Daniel C. Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2023-04-11:/blog/on-the-liberating-constraints-of-truth-and-virtue.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Have you noticed that schools often have a mission to equip students to change or even to remake the world? That they view liberty as simply the state of being unfettered, so that all constraints must be abolished in order for man to be truly free? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chesterton recognized that this …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Have you noticed that schools often have a mission to equip students to change or even to remake the world? That they view liberty as simply the state of being unfettered, so that all constraints must be abolished in order for man to be truly free? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chesterton recognized that this romantic view tends not toward freedom but to nothingness, not toward empowerment of the self, but to the diminishment of the world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[T]he moderns imagine that romance would exist most perfectly in a complete state of what they call liberty. They think that if a man makes a gesture it would be a startling and romantic matter that the sun should fall from the sky. But the startling and romantic thing about the sun is that it does not fall from the sky. They are seeking under every shape and form a world where there are no limitations&amp;mdash;that is, a world where there are no outlines; that is, a world where there are no shapes. There is nothing baser than that infinity. They say they wish to be as strong as the universe, but they really wish the whole universe as weak as themselves.
&amp;ndash;G.K. Chesteron, &lt;em&gt;On Certain Modern Writers and the Institution of the Family&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An education dedicated to liberating students from all limitations, including reality itself, is not merely in error&amp;mdash;it is tragic. It is like sending out a mariner to chart his course, but rather than providing him with a compass, telling him that he has been freed from the constraints of direction...and then wishing him well. Classical education recognizes that true liberty is found in a life constrained by virtue and conformed to the truth. We will not send out sailors without a compass. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Place of the Political and the Transcendent in Education</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-the-place-of-the-political-and-the-transcendent-in-education.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-28T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-28T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel C. Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2023-01-28:/blog/on-the-place-of-the-political-and-the-transcendent-in-education.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Are you exhausted by the partisan rancor that has engulfed our schools? Do you resent the incessant indoctrination going on in classrooms and wonder what can be done? It begins with recognizing the difference between the symptoms and the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is no secret that K-12 education in America …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Are you exhausted by the partisan rancor that has engulfed our schools? Do you resent the incessant indoctrination going on in classrooms and wonder what can be done? It begins with recognizing the difference between the symptoms and the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is no secret that K-12 education in America has become a hotbed of puerile activism, the challenge is to see beyond the immediate controversies. The answer to the toxic politicization of our schools is not an equally puerile counter-activism. We do not need ideological &amp;ldquo;balance.&amp;rdquo; What we need is a reorientation toward the transcendent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classical classroom is not simply stacked with political allies, similarly intent on rearranging the shadows in the cave for &amp;ldquo;our&amp;rdquo; side. No, classical schools are filled with teachers leading students on an ascent up out of the cave, so that in maturity, they will become virtuous citizens whose love of country begins with an allegiance to the truth. All education is inherently political, but done right, it is concerned with wisdom, not winning; with understanding not activism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winston Churchill famously said that &amp;ldquo;[t]he empires of the future will be empires of the mind.&amp;rdquo; At Columbus Classical Academy, we are building empires of knowledge and virtue. We will not bend our instruction to the fleeting controversies of the moment, but neither will we preoccupy ourselves with those small-minded partisans who insist on making our schools instruments of political expedience.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Enduring Importance of Humble Virtue</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-the-enduring-importance-of-humble-virtue.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-11T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-11T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel C. Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2023-01-11:/blog/on-the-enduring-importance-of-humble-virtue.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do claims of &amp;ldquo;virtue&amp;rdquo; come off as insolent and provocative? Do those who talk about virtue seem like self-righteous prudes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impression is not entirely unearned. Often those who invoke the moral law take on an air of superiority rather than the introspection that self-awareness demands. In our hypocrisy, we …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do claims of &amp;ldquo;virtue&amp;rdquo; come off as insolent and provocative? Do those who talk about virtue seem like self-righteous prudes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impression is not entirely unearned. Often those who invoke the moral law take on an air of superiority rather than the introspection that self-awareness demands. In our hypocrisy, we are not quick enough to recognize our own depravity before we decry it in others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as the old adage goes, &amp;ldquo;hypocrisy is the homage that vice pays to virtue.&amp;rdquo; The answer is not to dismantle virtue, as some would have it, but to humbly acknowledge our own iniquity and then be about the business of forming good and virtuous habits that build character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the aim of a classical education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many ideologies ascendant today, including within our schools, either redefine virtue as the unqualified pursuit of self-interest, or insist that the capacity for virtue depends entirely upon allegiance to a particular identity group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These distortions are not exclusive to the political left or right. Ayn Rand&amp;rsquo;s objectivist libertarianism declares the atomizing &amp;ldquo;Virtue of Selfishness&amp;rdquo; just as Marxist humanism proclaims the balkanizing virtue of revolutionary class struggle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as Solzhenitsyn recognized, his oppressors were not uniquely wicked nor were he and his fellow victims simply good. Instead, he saw that &amp;ldquo;[t]he line separating good and evil passes not through states, nor between classes, nor between political parties either&amp;mdash;but right through every human heart...&amp;rdquo; His, theirs, yours, and mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, like Chesterton, we at Columbus Classical Academy respond to the question &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with the world today?&amp;rdquo; by answering: &amp;ldquo;I am,&amp;rdquo; so that our pursuit of virtue is not about planting a flag of self-righteousness, but rather about planting the seeds of humility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>New Year, Old Truths: An Invitation from Columbus Classical Academy</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/new-year-old-truths-an-invitation-from-columbus-classical-academy.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-01T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-01T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel C. Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2023-01-01:/blog/new-year-old-truths-an-invitation-from-columbus-classical-academy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever asked the question, &amp;ldquo;What philosophy does my child&amp;rsquo;s school teach?&amp;rdquo; If not, perhaps this New Year is the perfect occasion to do so. Perhaps, upon reflection, you will conclude that now is the right time to discover anew the old truths that are the foundations of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever asked the question, &amp;ldquo;What philosophy does my child&amp;rsquo;s school teach?&amp;rdquo; If not, perhaps this New Year is the perfect occasion to do so. Perhaps, upon reflection, you will conclude that now is the right time to discover anew the old truths that are the foundations of a good education. This New Year, I invite you to consider Columbus Classical Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G.K. Chesterton once observed that &amp;ldquo;[e]very education teaches a philosophy&amp;hellip;.&amp;rdquo; He could have added that every education also emerges from a philosophy. What you believe&amp;mdash;about man and his place in the world&amp;mdash;will determine what kind of education you desire for your children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical education, prevalent in the West for over 2,000 years, begins with the recognition that man, by nature, is neither virtuous nor knowledgeable, and that students must be taught both to know and to love what is true, good, and beautiful, and be formed to live a life in the light of this knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most formal schooling in America used to pursue this end&amp;mdash;imperfectly, but sincerely&amp;mdash;by instructing children in the liberal arts and sciences in academic settings that valued knowledge and demanded virtue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practical terms, this meant reading the classics of history and literature, not because they are old, but because they are timeless, introducing students to the real and imagined heroes and villains, tragedies and triumphs, of our nation, culture, and world; teaching civics, not partisan politics, that illuminates the historical and philosophical foundations of our public institutions; science that seeks to understand, not merely subdue, the natural world; Latin, mathematics, the fine arts, and physical education to develop discipline and a fondness for beauty; teachers who lead and instruct rather than guide and facilitate; and an ordered classroom that demands moral character and self-control. It was the education of our nation&amp;rsquo;s Founders, informed by the principles underlying the birth and formation of the American republic itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While one may find fragments or remnants of classical teaching in some schools today, this time-honored approach now exists largely on the margins of the educational landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern education overwhelmingly proceeds from&amp;mdash;and teaches&amp;mdash;a very different philosophy: that man is by nature essentially good, that knowledge depends upon his perceptions rather than the things he perceives, and therefore that schools should guide students through a process of self-realization and personal growth. Instead of conforming one&amp;rsquo;s life to objective reality, students are encouraged to conform reality to their natural inclinations as a path to authenticity, life&amp;rsquo;s overriding virtue. Knowledge is valued principally for its utility in this pursuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In rare but extreme cases&amp;mdash;those grabbing headlines&amp;mdash;schools have embraced a denial of human nature itself, and with it the very concepts of truth, goodness, and beauty. On this view, man and his world are infinitely malleable, and students should be encouraged to abolish and re-create their reality, values, history&amp;mdash;even themselves&amp;mdash;in accordance with their own aspirations and wills. Virtue is a mirage. Truth is a tool of domination. Man is the measure&amp;mdash;and the maker&amp;mdash;of all things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While educational experts may trumpet the &amp;ldquo;science of learning,&amp;rdquo; disclaiming ideological influence, it is ultimately these philosophies, passed down through schools of education, that are behind much of that science, as well as many commonplace features of the modern classroom, like: student-led, experiential learning that elevates a child&amp;rsquo;s proclivities over curricular rigor; an abundance of technology and a paucity of books; group and project-based skill development instead of individual attainment of knowledge; social studies and language arts that view words and institutions primarily as tools for social change; science as a means to political &amp;ldquo;progress&amp;rdquo;; teachers who are partners in the &amp;ldquo;co-construction&amp;rdquo; of knowledge; and a sustained, inward-looking emphasis on personal identity and self-expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some will happily acknowledge these points of departure, insisting that classical education is stale, stifling, and obsolete, and that modern schooling gets it right. To be fair, not all modern innovations in education are uniformly bad. What is more, excellent teachers and administrators charged with their implementation often do so without an awareness of their philosophical underpinnings, motivated by a genuine desire to see students thrive. But, as The Bard would say, &amp;ldquo;therein lies the rub.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even by its own measures, modern education is not accomplishing its (misguided) objectives. The nation&amp;rsquo;s most recent report card is less than impressive. And a study from the Yale Center for Emotional Intelligence indicates that the most common emotions American teens feel about school are, &amp;ldquo;tired,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;stressed,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;bored.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s just teens,&amp;rdquo; you might say. But it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be. When schools impose upon students the Sisyphean burden of constructing their own knowledge, creating their own values, and defining their own identities rather than imparting to them a deep and broad understanding of their history, culture, faith, and world, is it any wonder that they gain neither wisdom nor fulfillment in the vain pursuit of themselves?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet &amp;ldquo;there is a tide in the affairs of men&amp;hellip;.&amp;rdquo; Today, public and private school parents, concerned citizens, and many teachers themselves have started to take heed, not just of the troubling headlines but of the true purpose of education itself. Here in our city, with the help of Hillsdale College and its world-class, K-12 curriculum, Columbus Classical Academy is restoring the foundations of a good education, opening its doors this Fall to students in grades K-8. In time, CCA will give rise to the greatest of earthly fortunes: knowledgeable citizens, souls with a longing for the truth, young men and women who know what is good and possess the courage to pursue it. Our city needs more Solomon, less Sisyphus. We will not miss the tide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you desire an education founded upon knowledge, virtue, and excellence for your child, consider Columbus Classical Academy. I promise, you&amp;rsquo;ll be glad you did. &lt;em&gt;Veritas et Virtus.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Importance of Struggle in a Good Education</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-the-importance-of-struggle-in-a-good-education.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-20T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-20T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel C. Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-12-20:/blog/on-the-importance-of-struggle-in-a-good-education.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shouldn&amp;rsquo;t school be fun? Don&amp;rsquo;t children do better when they are having a good time? Why must an excellent education be difficult? Despite appearances, these are questions of ends, not means&amp;mdash;of purpose, not pedagogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Struggle is an inherent part of classical education, not gratuitously but teleologically. Students …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shouldn&amp;rsquo;t school be fun? Don&amp;rsquo;t children do better when they are having a good time? Why must an excellent education be difficult? Despite appearances, these are questions of ends, not means&amp;mdash;of purpose, not pedagogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Struggle is an inherent part of classical education, not gratuitously but teleologically. Students must acquire knowledge that they do not naturally possess and form character that they will not naturally develop. This requires hard work and discipline on the part of teacher and student alike. But the result is a lasting capacity for genuine happiness&amp;mdash;what Aristotle called &amp;ldquo;that activity of the soul in accord with virtue.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has learned to play a musical instrument well understands this. A good pianist diligently practices scales and arpeggios, not because it is fun or easy, but because doing so yields technical mastery and provides the foundations for appreciation of music theory. The toil serves a worthy end. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sisyphus is miserable on account of the futility of his task, not its difficulty. He lacks hope, not because the stone is heavy but because he carries it nowhere. Camus insisted that we must imagine Sisyphus happy, but of course, he is not. Modern education invites him to simply put down the rock and play in the sand&amp;mdash;but the futility remains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical schools recognize that it is only sincere struggle with a noble purpose that makes for true happiness. To paraphrase Lewis: &amp;ldquo;Aim for virtue and you will get fun &amp;lsquo;thrown in&amp;rsquo;; aim for fun and you will get neither.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>On Holding Sudents’ Emotions Accountable to the Truth</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-holding-sudents-emotions-accountable-to-the-truth.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-15T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-15T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel C. Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-12-15:/blog/on-holding-sudents-emotions-accountable-to-the-truth.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever wonder why disagreement now seems impossible? Why debate only leads to greater conflict, not greater clarity? It is the inevitable consequence of generations of Americans being taught to seek and to love themselves rather than the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical education restores reason to its rightful place in the ordering of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever wonder why disagreement now seems impossible? Why debate only leads to greater conflict, not greater clarity? It is the inevitable consequence of generations of Americans being taught to seek and to love themselves rather than the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical education restores reason to its rightful place in the ordering of man&amp;rsquo;s faculties, not by teaching that feelings shouldn&amp;rsquo;t matter, but by recognizing that neither should they rule. As C.S. Lewis recognized: &amp;ldquo;The heart never takes the place of the head; but it can, and should, obey it.&amp;rdquo; We teach students the broad body of human knowledge&amp;mdash;literature, history, philosophy, natural science, mathematics, Latin, the arts&amp;mdash;to develop in them both the capacity and the desire to hold their emotions accountable to the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern education endeavors to make students feel good, not to help make them become good. So opinions are expressed by declaring &amp;ldquo;I feel&amp;rdquo; rather than &amp;ldquo;I think,&amp;rdquo; and experiences described as &amp;ldquo;my truths,&amp;rdquo; impervious to contradiction, all in the name of emotional health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet divorced from the truth, disagreements are little more than a battle of feelings versus feelings, resolvable only by power, not persuasion&amp;mdash;by force, not philosophy. Teaching the young to shout their feelings more loudly rather than to think about them more clearly cannot restore the deliberation, reflection, and choice that is the foundation of a free and flourishing republic. We must begin teaching our children to know and to love the truth again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disagree with me? Wonderful. Think I am wrong? Even better. But let&amp;rsquo;s stop pretending that we just feel differently.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Humble Pursuit of True Beauty</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-the-humble-pursuit-of-true-beauty.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-08T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-08T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel C. Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-12-08:/blog/on-the-humble-pursuit-of-true-beauty.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Believe that &amp;ldquo;beauty is in the eye of the beholder&amp;rdquo;? That Notre Dame Cathedral is considered more beautiful than a strip mall only on account of prevailing social norms? That when it comes to matters of aesthetics, &amp;ldquo;to each his own&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical schools part ways with modern education in their …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Believe that &amp;ldquo;beauty is in the eye of the beholder&amp;rdquo;? That Notre Dame Cathedral is considered more beautiful than a strip mall only on account of prevailing social norms? That when it comes to matters of aesthetics, &amp;ldquo;to each his own&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical schools part ways with modern education in their recognition that beauty is more than an arbitrary, personal sentiment or an imposed, social construct. We hold that beauty is objective and that one&amp;rsquo;s taste for the beautiful can either be well-ordered or disordered. The purpose of education in the arts is to form in students a knowledge and love of what is most beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, man&amp;rsquo;s understanding of beauty will always be imperfect and incomplete. But a lack of comprehensive knowledge of the beautiful does not render it incoherent. That science has never formulated an adequate &amp;ldquo;theory of everything&amp;rdquo; does not mean we know nothing of physics at all. It simply requires humility in the pursuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But consider the idea of music itself. The very distinction between a cacophony of sounds on the one hand, and musical expression on the other, is itself a rejection of modern conceptions of beauty. And no wonder. The word cacophony derives from the Greek kakophonos, meaning ill-sounding; the word music from the Greek mousike tekhne, meaning art of the muses. Are we really prepared to declare music class the mere study of noise?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is much beauty in the world. Let us be about the business of giving our children the eyes to see it and the ears to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry><entry><title>On What Makes a School Excellent</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/on-what-makes-a-school-excellent.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-01T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-01T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel C. Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-12-01:/blog/on-what-makes-a-school-excellent.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What makes a school excellent? It starts with a recognition that equality &amp;ldquo;has no place in the world of the mind&amp;rdquo;. Yes, all men are created equal. But their ideas, philosophies, art, literature, governments, cultures are not. Sound pretentious, even anti-democratic? Consider the alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratizing knowledge yields not excellence, but …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What makes a school excellent? It starts with a recognition that equality &amp;ldquo;has no place in the world of the mind&amp;rdquo;. Yes, all men are created equal. But their ideas, philosophies, art, literature, governments, cultures are not. Sound pretentious, even anti-democratic? Consider the alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratizing knowledge yields not excellence, but a triumph of the mediocre and a taste for the ordinary. Such schooling can be &amp;ldquo;excellent&amp;rdquo; only in the same way that a bulldozer can be &amp;ldquo;excellent,&amp;rdquo; i.e., to the extent it is effective at abolishing distinctions and demolishing hierarchies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical schools teach every student not what is most appealing to democratic sensibilities, but what is most excellent for an educated citizen: Goethe, not Grisham; Prokofiev, not Presley; Machiavelli, not Maddow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As C.S. Lewis observed, &amp;ldquo;[b]eauty is not democratic; she reveals herself more to the few than to the many, more to the persistent and disciplined seekers than to the careless. Virtue is not democratic; she is achieved by those who pursue her more hotly than most men. Truth is not democratic; she demands special talents and special industry in those to whom she gives her favours. Political democracy is doomed if it tries to extend its demand for equality into these higher spheres. Ethical, intellectual, or aesthetic democracy is death. A truly democratic education&amp;mdash;one which will preserve democracy&amp;mdash;must be, in its own field, ruthlessly aristocratic, shamelessly &amp;lsquo;high-brow&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you desire an excellent education for your child? One befitting a citizen of our democratic republic? It begins with renewing our belief in excellence itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Headmaster's Notes"></category></entry></feed>