<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>CCA Blog - News</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/feeds/news.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://columbusclassical.org/blog/</id><updated>2022-10-14T10:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>We're In Contract!</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/were-in-contract.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-10-14T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Columbus Classical Academy</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-10-14:/blog/were-in-contract.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're excited to announce that we are officially
In Contract!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CCA is currently in contract on a property in the Polaris area north of Columbus. The location is highly accessible, as travel time from virtually all of the major school districts in the Columbus area to the prospective site is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're excited to announce that we are officially
In Contract!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CCA is currently in contract on a property in the Polaris area north of Columbus. The location is highly accessible, as travel time from virtually all of the major school districts in the Columbus area to the prospective site is under 25 minutes. However, pursuant to our confidentiality obligations under the pending purchase agreement, we are not permitted to disclose the specific property at this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay in touch for updates!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="News"></category></entry><entry><title>Applications Now Open!</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/applications-now-open.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-10-03T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-10-03T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Columbus Classical Academy</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-10-03:/blog/applications-now-open.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are excited to announce that our early application period opens TODAY, Monday, October 3rd, 2022. Early application will be open until January 15th, 2023. Applications are available on our &lt;a href="https://columbusclassical.org/admissions.html" target="_blank"&gt;Admissions page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications can be submitted via USPS mail or email. Please read all instructions when downloading, filling out, and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are excited to announce that our early application period opens TODAY, Monday, October 3rd, 2022. Early application will be open until January 15th, 2023. Applications are available on our &lt;a href="https://columbusclassical.org/admissions.html" target="_blank"&gt;Admissions page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications can be submitted via USPS mail or email. Please read all instructions when downloading, filling out, and submitting an application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Please note: attendance at an information night is required if you move forward with an application. For a list of information nights, see our &lt;a href="https://columbusclassical.org/events.html" target="_blank"&gt;Events page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="News"></category></entry><entry><title>CCA Announces Our Academic Dean</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/cca-announces-our-academic-dean.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-09-20T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-09-20T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Columbus Classical Academy</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-09-20:/blog/cca-announces-our-academic-dean.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce that Sarah Spaulding has joined our team as Academic Dean. Mrs. Spaulding comes to CCA with years of experience in classical education, including as a founding member at a Hillsdale College Member School, as well as in teacher training and professional development, and literacy mastery …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce that Sarah Spaulding has joined our team as Academic Dean. Mrs. Spaulding comes to CCA with years of experience in classical education, including as a founding member at a Hillsdale College Member School, as well as in teacher training and professional development, and literacy mastery. She brings a wealth of experience and abiding passion for directing young people's hearts and minds toward the Good, the True, and the Beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome, Mrs. Spaulding! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more on our &lt;a href="https://columbusclassical.org/faculty-staff.html" target="_blank"&gt;Faculty &amp;amp; Staff page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="https://github.com/columbusclassical/columbusclassical.github.io/blob/main/images/faculty-staff/sarah-spaulding.jpg?raw=true" width="500 px"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="News"></category></entry><entry><title>Welcome!</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/welcome.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-16T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-16T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Gibson</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-08-16:/blog/welcome.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is my privilege to welcome you to Columbus Classical Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are honored and humbled by your interest in our school and grateful that you have considered entrusting us with the education of your children. It is a solemn and wonderful charge to impart to students the knowledge and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is my privilege to welcome you to Columbus Classical Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are honored and humbled by your interest in our school and grateful that you have considered entrusting us with the education of your children. It is a solemn and wonderful charge to impart to students the knowledge and virtue upon which responsible and joyful lives are built. Whether or not you ever enroll your child at CCA, we welcome you to explore our school and to inquire with us at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbus Classical Academy is a Hillsdale College Curriculum School, utilizing Hillsdale&amp;rsquo;s world-class and distinctively American, classical curriculum. Because we recognize that all education is both immanently personal and at the same time inherently social and political, students receive an education befitting not only a human being, but also an American citizen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hillsdale curriculum is rigorous, integrated, and sequential, grounded in the liberal arts and sciences and the Western canon. Every child studies literature, mathematics, history, civics, the natural sciences, Latin, the fine arts, physical education, and philosophy. These disciplines are taught using time-tested, teacher-led pedagogical methods, which include rigorous phonics instruction, explicit grammar lessons, and memorization and recitation. Instruction is complemented by the use of manipulatives in the teaching of arithmetic at the earliest grades. Handwriting and cursive lessons in written expression, use of the Socratic method, and close and critical reading of the classics and primary source texts are employed as students mature. At the conclusion of their time at CCA, students will possess a broad and deep body of knowledge about their world, their culture, their nation, and themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But CCA is more than just an academic institution. It is also a place of moral formation, where virtue is modeled, practiced, honored, and expected. We maintain that there are objective, moral laws to which all are accountable, and that without knowledge of the good and a desire to pursue it, man can be neither virtuous nor truly free. Our embrace of the classical virtues points us beyond ourselves to what is eternally significant, recognizing as did our nation&amp;rsquo;s founders that: &amp;ldquo;Religion, morality, and knowledge, being necessary to good government and the happiness of mankind, schools and the means of education shall forever be encouraged.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That proper, formal schooling is good and necessary, however, does not alone make it sufficient to the life of man. Parents are the first and primary teachers of their children. And because we at CCA hold that natural bond and relationship in high esteem, you will know what your children are learning, and your input on how best to engage and inspire them will be encouraged. Even more, your commitment to supporting and nurturing their moral and academic development at home will be essential. We are only a part of the task that is raising mature, joyful, responsible adults. We cannot do our part without you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an institution, Columbus Classical Academy is not yet a year old. But as an idea, as a philosophy of education, as &amp;ldquo;the real community of man, . . . of the potential knowers,&amp;rdquo; as Allan Bloom describes it, our school is more than 2,300 years old. We invite you to join us in the Great Conversation, to partner with us in passing down our incomparable cultural, religious and political inheritance to the next generation, and to pursue lives of knowledge and virtue together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to Columbus Classical Academy. &lt;em&gt;Veritas et Virtus.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;Daniel C. Gibson&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="News"></category></entry><entry><title>CCA Announces Our Headmaster</title><link href="https://columbusclassical.org/blog/cca-announces-our-headmaster.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-15T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-15T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Columbus Classical Academy</name></author><id>tag:columbusclassical.org,2022-08-15:/blog/cca-announces-our-headmaster.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;CCA has tapped Daniel Gibson to serve as the founding headmaster of the school. Gibson, a graduate of Davidson College and Stanford Law School, was a partner at the Columbus law firm, Bricker &amp;amp; Eckler LLP, and left his position at the firm to take on the role of headmaster at …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;CCA has tapped Daniel Gibson to serve as the founding headmaster of the school. Gibson, a graduate of Davidson College and Stanford Law School, was a partner at the Columbus law firm, Bricker &amp;amp; Eckler LLP, and left his position at the firm to take on the role of headmaster at CCA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I am so blessed to be part of the founding of Columbus Classical Academy," said Gibson. "I truly believe in the mission of a classical education to instill in students the knowledge and virtue upon which independent, responsible, and joyful lives are built and am grateful to the CCA board for entrusting me with the leadership of this good and necessary work."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome, Mr. Gibson! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more on our &lt;a href="https://columbusclassical.org/faculty-staff.html" target="_blank"&gt;Faculty &amp;amp; Staff page&lt;/a&gt;, or read Mr. Gibson's &lt;a href="https://columbusclassical.org/welcome.html"&gt;welcome message&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://columbusclassical.org/images/faculty-staff/dan.jpg" width="300 px"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://columbusclassical.org/images/dgibson.jpg" width="300 px"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Gibson, &lt;em&gt;Headmaster&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="News"></category></entry></feed>